<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <id>https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog</id>
    <title>Katelyn's UI Portfolio Blog</title>
    <updated>2024-12-06T16:58:00.000Z</updated>
    <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog"/>
    <subtitle>Katelyn's UI Portfolio Blog</subtitle>
    <icon>https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/img/favicon.ico</icon>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Design Interviews]]></title>
        <id>https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/design-interviews</id>
        <link href="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/design-interviews"/>
        <updated>2024-12-06T16:58:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Videos from Ricardo Hernandez Perez, CareerFoundry, and DesignWithArash]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="videos-from-ricardo-hernandez-perez-careerfoundry-and-designwitharash">Videos from Ricardo Hernandez Perez, CareerFoundry, and DesignWithArash<a class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Videos from Ricardo Hernandez Perez, CareerFoundry, and DesignWithArash" title="Direct link to Videos from Ricardo Hernandez Perez, CareerFoundry, and DesignWithArash" href="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/design-interviews#videos-from-ricardo-hernandez-perez-careerfoundry-and-designwitharash">​</a></h2>
<p>Interviews are a notoriously daunting process for many, especially those just starting out in an industry or any professional environment. To summarize the process in a single word, with all the preparation and knowledge that goes into a successful interview, is a difficult task. But in the context of a design interview, I believe perspective is the single most important concept to consider.</p>
<p>After watching these three videos from people with experience in the design industry, and seeing their advice for interviewees, I was unsurprised by many of the common threads: being self-aware, articulate, concise, and simply prepared were clearly emphasized. But I was more surprised by the unspoken undertone of many of those principles: being able to present and expand your perspective. A successful interview should be able to tell the interviewer what kind of person you would be to work with. Being able to articulate how you think, your process, and challenges you've overcome is a good way to illustrate your adaptability, and how they could expect you to respond to similar situations in their work environment. Being self-reflective, and demonstrating that you've been able to progress and learn from your mistakes is also valued--many interviewees get too caught up in fear of presenting themself as capable of mistakes to convey this effectively. And illustrating that same curiosity, building your perspective of what your work experience would be like if you were hired, is not just good for your own understanding, but is often appreciated by interviewers who want to see your passion and thoughtfulness about the position; they want you to want the job, and that usually requires a deep understanding of what that job truly means.</p>
<p>Videos:</p>
<ul><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=j07li1MUIa4" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Ricardo Hernandez Perez</a></li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vu3xcQm7cEo" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">CareerFoundry</a></li><li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZtN3yHIWuRY" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">DesignWithArash</a></li></ul>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="An interviewer and interviewee sit across from each other. The image is cropped such that we can only see their arms and the desk. The interviewee is annotating a highlighted document during the interview, while the interviewee sits attentively with their hands folded." src="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/assets/images/designInterviewImage-f956a57c76792ee315019ffa5942fe23.jpeg" width="6000" height="3376" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Though design interviews may have their own procedures outside of this stereotypical interview setup, the core principle of presenting oneself and being able to have a productive conversation with the interviewer remains. From <a href="https://stock.adobe.com/search?k=interview&amp;search_type=usertyped&amp;asset_id=276831797" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Adobe Stock</a></p>]]></content>
        <category label="WordJournal" term="WordJournal"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[The UIUN - An Exercise in Accessibility]]></title>
        <id>https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/uiun</id>
        <link href="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/uiun"/>
        <updated>2024-11-15T16:58:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[The UIUN, or User Interface United Nations, is an exercise intended to give learning designers some hands-on experience thinking about inclusive design--and reckoning with some of the reasons so many UI fail in this regard. For the exercise, each member of the group was assigned a certain population, and tasked with researching and presenting their accessibility needs. Afterwards, the group would negotiate and prioritize the design requirements derived from these needs, and allocate a set amount of resources on which could be implemented into our hypothetical web design.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The UIUN, or User Interface United Nations, is an exercise intended to give learning designers some hands-on experience thinking about inclusive design--and reckoning with some of the reasons so many UI fail in this regard. For the exercise, each member of the group was assigned a certain population, and tasked with researching and presenting their accessibility needs. Afterwards, the group would negotiate and prioritize the design requirements derived from these needs, and allocate a set amount of resources on which could be implemented into our hypothetical web design.</p>
<p>My group was color vision deficiency (CVD), better known as color blindness.</p>
<p>You can view the full presentation here:</p>
<iframe title="UIUN Color Vision Deficiency Presentation" src="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/e/2PACX-1vQ_6IVo7bonuABM50WZpxqvO0CMDc2XcWpeGLnNnFCHR8CXKieSt1bgRTjhfhcewHrY-3igWzkPsKLc/embed?start=false&amp;loop=false&amp;delayms=30000" frameborder="0" width="960" height="569" allowfullscreen="true" mozallowfullscreen="true" webkitallowfullscreen="true"></iframe><table></table>
<p>My initial findings were that:</p>
<ul><li>CVD affects 4.5% of the population, or 300 million people globally.</li><li><p>There are many different types of CVD, which affect color perception differently.</p><ul><li>Most commonly, CVD affects the ability to discriminate between red and green.</li><li>Other types include tritanopia, which affects yellow vs pink, red vs purple, and blue vs green.</li><li>In rare cases, and associated with more significant visual impairments, someone may be completely unable to see in color.</li></ul></li></ul>
<p>4.5% is a large number when we're talking about a group that could potentially be excluded by poor design decisions. But, with the varying types of CVD, it was clear not everyone with it has the same experience--and, by extension, a solution that worked for one person with CVD would be unlikely to work for the entire population. What we needed was:</p>
<ul><li>Not to focus too much on the hues in use, since not everyone will perceive them the same way.</li><li>To focus on making design elements distinct, regardless of what hue they were perceived to be.</li><li>To give some additional cue if color is used to imply meaning.</li></ul>
<p>These principles translate fairly immediately into design ideas:</p>
<ul><li>Use additional, <em>meaningful</em> symbols, labels, etc. to accompany color cues.</li><li>Make sure the values of our colors contrast enough, so that regardless of the parent hue, they are clearly differentiated.</li></ul>
<p>I once spent several minutes trying to piece together why my code, which had compiled and was working as expected, had a red parentheses, the color that usually indicates a syntax error. After coming up with nothing, I eventually discovered that what I had perceived as read was simply a magenta color that appeared red due to my low screen brightness--it was simply meant to color code a match with its closing parentheses. Sufficient contrast, or an additional symbol besides color, could have avoided the confusion entirely. I don't have CVD, and I could readily think of an instance where I would benefit from the same design changes that could help someone who does.</p>
<p>This revealed a strong underlying theme of this exercise. Inclusive design ideas don't exclusively help people with disabilities--they're often good considerations in general, helping a wide range of users beyond just the ones they were built for. For that reason, I was optimistic about the support I'd receive for my changes going into the negotiation process with my peers. I planned to emphasize color contrast within the values of the palette, since I expected non-color signifiers would not require much argument. I was prompt about prioritizing this aspect of the palette, and with a few additional requirements for colors or color combinations to favor or avoid being wrapped into the original (many of which came from our photosensitivity representative), I was able to secure both my major design suggestions here.</p>
<p>Overall, the negotiations went very smoothly. My peers seemed very mindful of the importance of all the design considerations presented, even ones that did not directly assist their population. I was most surprised by the overlap between myself and the non-native English speakers representative, as at first glance there wouldn't appear to be much overlap between CVD and multilingual populations. However, acknowledging that many multilingual users are going to have different cultural backgrounds, it brought up the important consideration that the meanings of colors are not universal. People with CVD may miss color-indicated meanings due to a difference in how they perceive the colors, and people with different cultural backgrounds than a designer may miss the meaning because they have a different association with the color. For both, use of additional cues to suggest the content's meaning would be beneficial. As for the groups that were hardest to convince, our representative of baby boomers diverged the most vocally from me. Though there were some places our populations' needs overlapped, such as having good color contrast, the areas where their needs diverged took many of our priorities elsewhere. She was advocating for things like screen reader support over something like non color-dependent cues.</p>
<p>I don't doubt that either of us acknowledge the usefulness of the other's proposals, but with the limited resources we had to allocate to our final picks, our priorities conflicted. I felt bad about ignoring the suggestions of many others whose proposals did not match well with mine, or who had less support for their suggestions overall. Not a single one of my peers' ideas were without purpose, and all would be helpful inclusions for accessibility. It seems to match many common trends in web design overall, where the less visible accessibility requirements go neglected--and, thanks to that lack of accesibility, it's not always simple for those populations to voice their needs to the people who could make these changes.</p>
<p>In conclusion, this exercise gave me a lot to think about, and many principles to carry into my future designs. My major takeaways from the activity were:</p>
<ul><li>Inclusive design helps more people than just those the designer had in mind.</li><li>Inclusive design is effortful, and without careful consideration, some important requirements may go overlooked.</li><li>It's a lot simpler to dedicate resources to following inclusive design principles from the beginning, instead of trying to find the resources to restructure things later on.</li></ul>
<p>Sources:</p>
<ul><li><a></a><a href="https://www.nei.nih.gov/learn-about-eye-health/eye-conditions-and-diseases/color-blindness/types-color-vision-deficiency" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://www.nei.nih.gov/learn-about-eye-health/eye-conditions-and-diseases/color-blindness/types-color-vision-deficiency</a></li><li><a></a><a href="https://www.desertvisioncenter.com/news/do-enchroma-glasses-work-to-treat-colorblindness/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://www.desertvisioncenter.com/news/do-enchroma-glasses-work-to-treat-colorblindness/</a></li><li><a></a><a href="https://www.colourblindawareness.org/colour-blindness/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://www.colourblindawareness.org/colour-blindness/</a></li><li><a></a><a href="https://www.boia.org/blog/what-is-color-blindness-accessibility" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://www.boia.org/blog/what-is-color-blindness-accessibility</a></li><li><a></a><a href="https://www.sarpy.gov/659/Election-Commission" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://www.sarpy.gov/659/Election-Commission</a></li></ul>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="An image showing a row of wooden blocks. The last several spell out &amp;quot;bility&amp;quot;, but the first few are tilted so that multiple faces are visible, spelling out either &amp;quot;usa&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;accesi&amp;quot;. The word can be read as either &amp;quot;usability&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;accessibility&amp;quot;." src="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/assets/images/uiunImage-ca5203c5e97401a89d3ae6f3061acd9a.jpeg" width="5296" height="3507" class="img_ev3q">
I like this image a lot, as I think it reflects one of my major takeaways from the exercise--that design choices often thought of as accessibility features often help usability in general. From <a href="https://stock.adobe.com/search?filters%5Bcontent_type%3Aphoto%5D=1&amp;filters%5Bcontent_type%3Aillustration%5D=1&amp;filters%5Bcontent_type%3Azip_vector%5D=1&amp;filters%5Bcontent_type%3Avideo%5D=1&amp;filters%5Bcontent_type%3Atemplate%5D=1&amp;filters%5Bcontent_type%3A3d%5D=1&amp;filters%5Bcontent_type%3Aaudio%5D=0&amp;filters%5Bfetch_excluded_assets%5D=1&amp;filters%5Binclude_stock_enterprise%5D=1&amp;filters%5Bis_editorial%5D=0&amp;filters%5Bfree_collection%5D=0&amp;filters%5Bcontent_type%3Aimage%5D=1&amp;k=accessibility&amp;order=relevance&amp;search_page=2&amp;get_facets=0&amp;search_type=pagination&amp;asset_id=396823252" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Adobe Stock</a></p>]]></content>
        <category label="Studies" term="Studies"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Inclusive Design II]]></title>
        <id>https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/inclusive-design-ii</id>
        <link href="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/inclusive-design-ii"/>
        <updated>2024-11-01T17:58:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Reading Don Norman's The Design of Everyday Things Chapter 4]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="reading-don-normans-the-design-of-everyday-things-chapter-4">Reading Don Norman's <em>The Design of Everyday Things</em> Chapter 4<a class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to reading-don-normans-the-design-of-everyday-things-chapter-4" title="Direct link to reading-don-normans-the-design-of-everyday-things-chapter-4" href="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/inclusive-design-ii#reading-don-normans-the-design-of-everyday-things-chapter-4">​</a></h2>
<p><em>Constraints are to design as laws are to society.</em></p>
<p>The many constraints we place within a design are a powerful tool in conveying how it is used. As Norman elaborates in this chapter, laws themselves are a form of cultural constraint.</p>
<p>Physical constraints limit what can be physically done with a thing, such as inserting an object into something or connecting two objects at a specific point. These are a useful way to deter incorrect actions and imply the correct ones, especially when they are clearly communicated, which can be done even in simple ways like through an object's physical structure.</p>
<p>Cultural constraints refer to the limits of our thinking within a cultural context. Some behaviors or symbols might be commonplace in one part of the world, but mean nothing at all, or something entirely different, in others. Cultural constraints limit a user's ability to interact with something, and may also limit a designer's ability to think about the universality of a design.</p>
<p>Semantic constraints refer to the context of a situation. Given the context and ultimate goals of an individual design, some operations may be more intuitive than they would be in another context.</p>
<p>Logical constraints are deductions a user can make, such as pieces of text going with the most adjacent heading.</p>
<p>All these constraints in total provide order to a design, but they can be difficult to balance, and due to their lack of universality can create accessibility issues as not all users will understand them the same way. Thus, it is important for any designer to have an understanding of how a wide variety of users will process different constraints.</p>
<p>Sources:</p>
<p>Norman, D. (2013). <em>The design of everyday things.</em> Basic Books. <a href="https://jnd.org/books/the-design-of-everyday-things-revised-and-expanded-edition/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Link</a></p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Three cars traveling the same direction down a narrow bridge that passes over train tracks, then a river channel." src="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/assets/images/inclusiveDesignIIImage-916c0eaa86f95f95989eafd85b6726cf.jpeg" width="8064" height="5040" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>This image matches Norman's example of the clashing of cultural constraints, where signals on who will proceed first over a one-lane bridge can mean the opposite in different regions. From <a href="https://stock.adobe.com/search?filters%5Bcontent_type%3Aphoto%5D=1&amp;filters%5Bcontent_type%3Aillustration%5D=1&amp;filters%5Bcontent_type%3Azip_vector%5D=1&amp;filters%5Bcontent_type%3Avideo%5D=1&amp;filters%5Bcontent_type%3Atemplate%5D=1&amp;filters%5Bcontent_type%3A3d%5D=1&amp;filters%5Bfetch_excluded_assets%5D=1&amp;filters%5Binclude_stock_enterprise%5D=1&amp;filters%5Bcontent_type%3Aimage%5D=1&amp;filters%5Bcontent_type%3Aaudio%5D=0&amp;filters%5Bis_editorial%5D=0&amp;filters%5Bfree_collection%5D=0&amp;k=car+on+narrow+bridge&amp;order=relevance&amp;limit=100&amp;search_page=1&amp;search_type=usertyped&amp;acp=&amp;aco=car+on+narrow+bridge&amp;get_facets=0&amp;asset_id=747254153" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Adobe Stock</a>.</p>]]></content>
        <category label="ApproximateAnalogy" term="ApproximateAnalogy"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Inclusive Design I]]></title>
        <id>https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/inclusive-design-i</id>
        <link href="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/inclusive-design-i"/>
        <updated>2024-11-01T16:58:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Reading from Steven Krug's Don't Make Me Think, Revisited: A Common Sense Approach to Web Usability Chapter 12]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="reading-from-steven-krugs-dont-make-me-think-revisited-a-common-sense-approach-to-web-usability-chapter-12">Reading from Steven Krug's <em>Don't Make Me Think, Revisited: A Common Sense Approach to Web Usability</em> Chapter 12<a class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to reading-from-steven-krugs-dont-make-me-think-revisited-a-common-sense-approach-to-web-usability-chapter-12" title="Direct link to reading-from-steven-krugs-dont-make-me-think-revisited-a-common-sense-approach-to-web-usability-chapter-12" href="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/inclusive-design-i#reading-from-steven-krugs-dont-make-me-think-revisited-a-common-sense-approach-to-web-usability-chapter-12">​</a></h2>
<p><em>Options</em> is a word that embodies the concepts of this chapter. Inclusive design can be a tricky problem since not all users have the same needs, and something that may be useful to one person might actively disrupt another. This issue, along with the time and resources involved in making a website widely accessible, are commonly blamed for why designers don't pursue accessibility options. But in modern design, where we have conveniences like accessibility menus that allow people to customize the features that best assist their experince, there's little need to attempt to respond to everyone's needs in a singular interface. By including different options to adjust the same base experience, we can allow users to individualize their experience.</p>
<p>Creating these options does still take resources on the designers' part, but it is a worthy effort to allow the most people possible to use a site comfortably. If enough people are willing to undertake that effort, we can make a more widely accessible internet, and perhaps contribute to even more tools along the way that can make accessibility features simpler to implement. The amount of accessibility-related resources readily available to developers has already increased greatly from the past. Krug offers easy starting points, like fixing widespread use issues, doing research on accessible web design, and starting with small things like alt text, clear heading structure, and color contrast to fix a few common accessibility issues.</p>
<p>Sources:</p>
<p>Krug, S. (2014). <em>Don’t make me think, revisited: A common sense approach to web usability</em> (Third edition). New Riders. <a href="https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.5555/2663393" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Link</a></p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="The modern accessibility icon, a representation of a person standing with both their arms stretched up." src="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/assets/images/inclusiveDesignIImage-ee2f5758e24a24f97f19e92adce50a2b.jpeg" width="3873" height="3873" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>This iconography has risen in popularity as the indicator for accesibility features online. From <a href="https://stock.adobe.com/search?k=modern+accessibility+icon&amp;search_type=usertyped&amp;asset_id=902722803" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Adobe Stock</a>.</p>]]></content>
        <category label="WordJournal" term="WordJournal"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Debriefing User Tests]]></title>
        <id>https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/debriefing-user-tests</id>
        <link href="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/debriefing-user-tests"/>
        <updated>2024-10-24T17:58:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Reading from Steven Krug's Don't Make Me Think, Revisited: A Common Sense Approach to Web Usability Pages 137-141]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="reading-from-steven-krugs-dont-make-me-think-revisited-a-common-sense-approach-to-web-usability-pages-137-141">Reading from Steven Krug's <em>Don't Make Me Think, Revisited: A Common Sense Approach to Web Usability</em> Pages 137-141<a class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to reading-from-steven-krugs-dont-make-me-think-revisited-a-common-sense-approach-to-web-usability-pages-137-141" title="Direct link to reading-from-steven-krugs-dont-make-me-think-revisited-a-common-sense-approach-to-web-usability-pages-137-141" href="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/debriefing-user-tests#reading-from-steven-krugs-dont-make-me-think-revisited-a-common-sense-approach-to-web-usability-pages-137-141">​</a></h2>
<p>For this quick reading on debriefing user testing from Steven Krug’s <em>Don’t Make Me Think</em>, I thought it best to summarize the contents in a tutorial. This reading was about what comes after user testing, when we can take the information gained from the test back to the design team and plan next steps.</p>
<ol><li>Create a list of nine problems observed during user testing, choosing three to offer to the group per session.</li><ol><li>Krug directs this advice at design teams: for smaller projects, offer up more of these problems at a time.</li></ol><li>Consider the cost-benefits of each issue to discern which are most critical for the most return.
Think about modifications before new features.</li><ol><li>Issues a user could self-correct are generally not of the highest priority.</li><li>Rank the most crucial problems from the collective list.</li></ol><li>Move forward with the top ten issues off the list.</li><li>Keep track of quick-fixes that did not make the top ten.</li><li>Make individual plans with the team as to how these issues will be approached.</li></ol>
<p>Sources:</p>
<p>Krug, S. (2014). <em>Don’t make me think, revisited: A common sense approach to web usability</em> (Third edition). New Riders. <a href="https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.5555/2663393" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Link</a></p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="A duo of peers with laptops, one looking at something on the other&amp;#39;s screen." src="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/assets/images/debriefUserTestImage-40979c8ea5ea48f096686943c913658d.jpeg" width="5168" height="3448" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Debriefing user testing should be an interactive processes within the team where everyone seeks to reach an understanding of the issues identified and their prioritization. From <a href="https://stock.adobe.com/search?filters%5Bcontent_type%3Aphoto%5D=1&amp;filters%5Bcontent_type%3Aillustration%5D=1&amp;filters%5Bcontent_type%3Azip_vector%5D=1&amp;filters%5Bcontent_type%3Avideo%5D=1&amp;filters%5Bcontent_type%3Atemplate%5D=1&amp;filters%5Bcontent_type%3A3d%5D=1&amp;filters%5Bfetch_excluded_assets%5D=1&amp;filters%5Binclude_stock_enterprise%5D=1&amp;filters%5Bcontent_type%3Aimage%5D=1&amp;filters%5Bcontent_type%3Aaudio%5D=0&amp;filters%5Bis_editorial%5D=0&amp;filters%5Bfree_collection%5D=0&amp;k=debrief&amp;order=relevance&amp;limit=100&amp;search_page=1&amp;search_type=usertyped&amp;acp=&amp;aco=debrief&amp;get_facets=0&amp;asset_id=253235562" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Adobe Stock</a>.</p>]]></content>
        <category label="Tutorial" term="Tutorial"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[User Testing]]></title>
        <id>https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/user-testing</id>
        <link href="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/user-testing"/>
        <updated>2024-10-24T16:58:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Reading from Steven Krug's Don't Make Me Think, Revisited: A Common Sense Approach to Web Usability Chapters 8 and 9, and Don Norman's The Design of Everyday Things Chapter 5]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="reading-from-steven-krugs-dont-make-me-think-revisited-a-common-sense-approach-to-web-usability-chapters-8-and-9-and-don-normans-the-design-of-everyday-things-chapter-5">Reading from Steven Krug's <em>Don't Make Me Think, Revisited: A Common Sense Approach to Web Usability</em> Chapters 8 and 9, and Don Norman's <em>The Design of Everyday Things</em> Chapter 5<a class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to reading-from-steven-krugs-dont-make-me-think-revisited-a-common-sense-approach-to-web-usability-chapters-8-and-9-and-don-normans-the-design-of-everyday-things-chapter-5" title="Direct link to reading-from-steven-krugs-dont-make-me-think-revisited-a-common-sense-approach-to-web-usability-chapters-8-and-9-and-don-normans-the-design-of-everyday-things-chapter-5" href="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/user-testing#reading-from-steven-krugs-dont-make-me-think-revisited-a-common-sense-approach-to-web-usability-chapters-8-and-9-and-don-normans-the-design-of-everyday-things-chapter-5">​</a></h2>
<p>These readings go into depth on the nature of user testing, and the nature of mistakes within a UI.</p>
<p><em>Don’t Make Me Think</em> covers the benefits and general flow of user testing. User testing allows us to gain insights from people with distance from the project–the designers, too used to their own system, can easily overlook issues entirely, leading to problems if they assume this means no issues remain. User testing does not need to be expensive, or even especially formal beyond following a general script and gaining consent for recording. Generally, the user will be told about the process, introduced to the home page, then given tasks to attempt on the site. The proctor will watch them perform these tasks, and the user will attempt to narrate their thought process, so that we can better understand what goes through the user’s mind as they navigate (or fail to) through the task.</p>
<p><em>The Design of Everyday Things</em> gives us some guidance on how we should respond to user mistakes that were identified in testing. It is very rarely (but not never) the fault of a human when an error occurs. In most cases, were we to improve our design by giving better signifiers or feedback, accounting for possible mistakes, and so on, we could have prevented the error entirely. User testing allows us to uncover such mistakes and adjust our system accordingly.</p>
<p>This section got me thinking about a design consideration that has been more in the public eye recently–the shift to digital UI in cars. Concerns have been expressed both by the public and regulatory agencies about the safety of digital interfaces, which draw users’ attention away from the road for more sustained periods than a traditional car function, like a knob to change speaker volume, is expected to.</p>
<p>Tesla has been at the forefront of digitizing vehicles. I referenced the images in <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YxEteR7myno" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">this video</a> to analyze their UI. The UI does retain many established signifiers of analog interfaces, such as the speaker icons to indicate where volume controls are located and heating icons for temperature adjustment. However, aside from the basic functionalities of a car, it is difficult to guess where more advanced functions would be tucked away. The same argument could be made for a traditional interface, but due to the all-inclusive nature of the screen display, I suspect many users would be inclined to spend more time searching than they would parsing traditional buttons or knobs.</p>
<p>The video also references Elon Musk’s idea that all inputs are a mistake, which seems like a radical expansion on the ideas expressed in <em>The Design of Everyday Things</em> that it is rarely a human user’s fault when something goes wrong, but an underlying flaw in the system. Musk’s idea is something more akin to any dependency on human interaction is an error in the system. Making a system operate as independently from a user as possible would remove the human error excuse, but it will also unveil the flaws within the system itself.</p>
<p>Sources:</p>
<p>Krug, S. (2014). <em>Don’t make me think, revisited: A common sense approach to web usability</em> (Third edition). New Riders. <a href="https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.5555/2663393" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Link</a></p>
<p>Norman, D. (2013). <em>The design of everyday things.</em> Basic Books. <a href="https://jnd.org/books/the-design-of-everyday-things-revised-and-expanded-edition/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Link</a></p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="A woman facing the camera, looking down at a tablet screen." src="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/assets/images/userTestingImage-a24d5235bb6b66c02dbce7dc10021a12.jpeg" width="4618" height="3082" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>The prominence of touch-screen tablets has had an effect on design conventions, such as the popularization of screen displays for cars. From <a href="https://stock.adobe.com/search?filters%5Bcontent_type%3Aphoto%5D=1&amp;filters%5Bcontent_type%3Aillustration%5D=1&amp;filters%5Bcontent_type%3Azip_vector%5D=1&amp;filters%5Bcontent_type%3Avideo%5D=1&amp;filters%5Bcontent_type%3Atemplate%5D=1&amp;filters%5Bcontent_type%3A3d%5D=1&amp;filters%5Bcontent_type%3Aaudio%5D=0&amp;filters%5Bfetch_excluded_assets%5D=1&amp;filters%5Binclude_stock_enterprise%5D=1&amp;filters%5Bis_editorial%5D=0&amp;filters%5Bfree_collection%5D=0&amp;filters%5Bcontent_type%3Aimage%5D=1&amp;k=ipad&amp;order=relevance&amp;search_page=1&amp;search_type=usertyped&amp;acp=&amp;aco=ipad&amp;get_facets=0&amp;asset_id=299088840" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Adobe Stock</a>.</p>]]></content>
        <category label="DirectedAnalysis" term="DirectedAnalysis"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mockups]]></title>
        <id>https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/mockups</id>
        <link href="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/mockups"/>
        <updated>2024-10-18T18:58:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Reading from Steven Krug's Don't Make Me Think, Revisited Simple Ideas on Presentation Design and Delivery Chapters 2 and 4]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="reading-from-steven-krugs-dont-make-me-think-revisited-a-common-sense-approach-to-web-usability-chapter-7-and-garr-reynoldss-presentation-zen-simple-ideas-on-presentation-design-and-delivery-chapters-2-and-4">Reading from Steven Krug's <em>Don't Make Me Think, Revisited: A Common Sense Approach to Web Usability</em> Chapter 7 and Garr Reynolds's <em>Presentation Zen: Simple Ideas on Presentation Design and Delivery</em> Chapters 2 and 4<a class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to reading-from-steven-krugs-dont-make-me-think-revisited-a-common-sense-approach-to-web-usability-chapter-7-and-garr-reynoldss-presentation-zen-simple-ideas-on-presentation-design-and-delivery-chapters-2-and-4" title="Direct link to reading-from-steven-krugs-dont-make-me-think-revisited-a-common-sense-approach-to-web-usability-chapter-7-and-garr-reynoldss-presentation-zen-simple-ideas-on-presentation-design-and-delivery-chapters-2-and-4" href="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/mockups#reading-from-steven-krugs-dont-make-me-think-revisited-a-common-sense-approach-to-web-usability-chapter-7-and-garr-reynoldss-presentation-zen-simple-ideas-on-presentation-design-and-delivery-chapters-2-and-4">​</a></h2>
<p>This set of readings covered a lot of ground when it came to considerations for a UI design. <em>Presentation Zen</em> discusses typography and images in these chapters. The readability of font is a crucial visual consideration, achieved by ensuring a font is suitably large and favoring sans serif fonts as a way to prevent issues of clarity at lower resolutions. Images are also emphasized as an important way to draw attention to a message. Labels tell much of the story behind a photo, and styling your photo in a harmonious way with the rest of the "slide" creates a more appealing and effective visual. <em>Don't Make Me Think</em> is a bit more diversified in its approach, discussing both the importance of communication within a UI. Home pages are emphasized as a way to serve users with an overview of crucial information quickly, and taglines are also endorsed as a way to be upfront with a website's goals. So, to encapsulate all the takeaways from these readings, I decided to sketch a UI that would touch on several of them. I began by choosing a random image from my camera roll to serve as a banner, and ended up with one of a butterfly. From this, I decided that the website would be a butterfly identification database. I added a tagline and broadcast the name of the site in a large, sans serif font for readability. A drop shadow around the white text ensures it doesn't fade into the background of the image.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="A sketch of a UI for a butterfly identifier. A photo of a gray butterfly on a leaf serves as the banner for the home page. The top navigation bar directs users to a &amp;quot;Home&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;About&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Identifier&amp;quot;, and &amp;quot;Conservation&amp;quot; page." src="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/assets/images/mockupsSketch-0c59506c8453f9f3b4d23c0b51111b4f.PNG" width="1254" height="985" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Sources:
Krug, S. (2014). <em>Don’t make me think, revisited: A common sense approach to web usability</em> (Third edition). New Riders. <a href="https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.5555/2663393" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Link</a>
Reynolds, G. (2019). <em>Presentation zen: Simple ideas on presentation design and delivery</em> (Third edition). New Riders.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="A blank billboard on the horizon." src="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/assets/images/mockupImage-7509f57cd4628f2ec519e1e69dbc8c5d.jpeg" width="7360" height="4912" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Since much of this reading makes references to billboards as a basic case for these design considerations, an image of a blank billboard felt apt. From <a href="https://stock.adobe.com/search?k=billboard&amp;search_type=usertyped&amp;asset_id=327644908" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Adobe Stock</a>.</p>]]></content>
        <category label="SketchInspo" term="SketchInspo"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Feedback]]></title>
        <id>https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/feedback</id>
        <link href="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/feedback"/>
        <updated>2024-10-18T17:58:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Reading from InVision]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="reading-from-invision">Reading from InVision<a class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Reading from InVision" title="Direct link to Reading from InVision" href="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/feedback#reading-from-invision">​</a></h2>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="A concept map of key points from the InVision feedback article, detailed below." src="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/assets/images/feedbackMap-f0e2ab9ef5945ddaea94bb2a77a7eeb6.PNG" width="2048" height="1010" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>For this reading, I chose to represent InVision's discussion on helpful feedback in a concept map, to help relate their ideas of good feedback and how feedback can get lost if not given properly and constructively. Two major types of feedback are identified: redirecting and reinforcing. As the names imply, redirecting feedback tell people what they can improve on, while reinforcing feedback tells them where they are already successful. Feedback is a delicate thing, as poorly-done feedback is perceived as criticism, and results in a less open exchange of ideas. Feedback is crucial to helping designers learn and improve, and being cognizant of these principles helps maximize the effectiveness of the feedback we provide. We often aren't aware of our own shortcomings, and our successes can often go unaddressed, so hearing about both helps keep us engaged.</p>
<p>Source: Kirkwood, J. (2018, October 4). How to give designers feedback they can actually use. InVision. <a href="https://www.invisionapp.com/inside-design/give-designers-feedback/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Link</a></p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Smiley, frowny, and neutral faces hover over a keyboard." src="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/assets/images/feedbackImage-d35f685f18a4ad3c269b13c1dff06a7c.jpeg" width="4256" height="2660" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>The most basic form of feedback we receive on online platforms, a star rating, often doesn't convey enough to be constructive. From <a href="https://stock.adobe.com/search?k=feedback&amp;search_type=usertyped&amp;asset_id=480329143" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Adobe Stock</a></p>]]></content>
        <category label="ConceptMap" term="ConceptMap"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Portfolio and Design Narratives]]></title>
        <id>https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/portfolio-design-narratives</id>
        <link href="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/portfolio-design-narratives"/>
        <updated>2024-10-16T17:58:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Reading from UXfolio]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="reading-from-uxfolio">Reading from UXfolio<a class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Reading from UXfolio" title="Direct link to Reading from UXfolio" href="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/portfolio-design-narratives#reading-from-uxfolio">​</a></h2>
<p><em>Design is to a UI as clothes are to a person.</em></p>
<p>A person's choice of fashion says a lot about them. Colors and styles convey detail about the wearer's personality and, in many professional contexts, determines if someone is taken seriously and if they're perceived to be taking the situation seriously. Since clothing is one of the first impressions we have of someone we're meeting, it tends to be emphasized greatly. Many of the same principles apply to UI. Color conveyances, typefaces, and so on are used to style a UI in a way that conveys something about the people behind it. It seems a common trend in UXfolio's collection of portfolio examples that many of them follow modern design conventions: sleek, clean, minimal in their palette, with splashes of color according to the designer's own tastes. Since a portfolio is used in professional contexts, and in many cases is a prospective employer's first impression of an applicant, it makes sense that these conventions emerge. It's much the same idea as wearing business attire to a job interview--it's an acknowledgement of the professional environment by following an established standard for that environment. Balancing a glimpse into the designer's character with the professional expectations of the format can be a difficult task, but when done with intentionality and moderation, a portfolio can have both professionalism and personality.</p>
<p>Source: Simon, K and Izsák, Á. (2024, July 31). 23 successful UX portfolio examples and a guide for creating yours. UXfolio. <a href="https://blog.uxfol.io/ux-portfolio-examples/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Link</a></p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="A person sitting on the rightmost of four chairs, dressed in business attire: a white blouse with a red jacket and pants." src="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/assets/images/portfoliosImage-c5066a31a80895ca0796dad7384a9544.jpeg" width="6709" height="4473" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>This person is clearly dressed professionally, but the red is a rare choice that conveys something about their personality. We can strive for much the same balance in a portfolio. From <a href="https://stock.adobe.com/search?k=job+interview&amp;search_type=usertyped&amp;asset_id=317001615" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Adobe Stock</a></p>]]></content>
        <category label="ApproximateAnalogy" term="ApproximateAnalogy"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Navigation and Values]]></title>
        <id>https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/navigation-and-values</id>
        <link href="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/navigation-and-values"/>
        <updated>2024-10-08T16:58:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Reading from Steven Krug's Don't Make Me Think, Revisited An Exercise for Individuals and Teams]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="reading-from-steven-krugs-dont-make-me-think-revisited-a-common-sense-approach-to-web-usability-chapter-6-and-colin-brecks-understanding-our-core-values-an-exercise-for-individuals-and-teams">Reading from Steven Krug's <em>Don't Make Me Think, Revisited: A Common Sense Approach to Web Usability</em> Chapter 6 and Colin Breck's <em>Understanding Our Core Values: An Exercise for Individuals and Teams</em><a class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to reading-from-steven-krugs-dont-make-me-think-revisited-a-common-sense-approach-to-web-usability-chapter-6-and-colin-brecks-understanding-our-core-values-an-exercise-for-individuals-and-teams" title="Direct link to reading-from-steven-krugs-dont-make-me-think-revisited-a-common-sense-approach-to-web-usability-chapter-6-and-colin-brecks-understanding-our-core-values-an-exercise-for-individuals-and-teams" href="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/navigation-and-values#reading-from-steven-krugs-dont-make-me-think-revisited-a-common-sense-approach-to-web-usability-chapter-6-and-colin-brecks-understanding-our-core-values-an-exercise-for-individuals-and-teams">​</a></h2>
<p><em>Hierarchy</em> is a word that embodies both the navigation and values components of this reading.</p>
<p>Krug’s discussion of navigation heavily emphasizes hierarchy. It is crucial for a viewer to know where they are within a site, an especially difficult task given the relative unknowns of navigating a website compared to a physical environment. Thus, hierarchy helps direct where users are and where they can get to from that point. Users’ choices when navigating a website are usually snap judgments with little conscious thought, so helping to inform those by providing a visual indicator of the organization flow of the website can lead to more accurate choices and less opportunities to get lost. Several of Krug’s major questions to ask about website navigation, including the page’s major sections, options at the current level, and position in the scheme of things, are logically embodied by a hierarchy, and a UI is well-served by reflecting that internal logic through its visual construction.</p>
<p>Hierarchy is also important in conversations of values. Colin Breck describes the likely problem that a company will resonate with many core values, but must limit its key values in order to adhere to them fully. Specifically, the text describes “second-tier” values that are encompassed within the two core values selected by a company.</p>
<p>Sources:
Krug, S. (2014). <em>Don’t make me think, revisited: A common sense approach to web usability</em> (Third edition). New Riders. <a href="https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.5555/2663393" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Link</a></p>
<p>Breck, C. (2020, February 2). *Understanding our core values: An exercise for individuals and teams. <a href="https://blog.colinbreck.com/understanding-our-core-values-an-exercise-for-individuals-and-teams/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Link</a></p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="An image displaying a flow of information organized into a hierarchy." src="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/assets/images/navAndValuesImage-7ef588edcec6e8c04804a80d66bcfb8b.jpeg" width="4763" height="3150" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>A simple image to represent hierarchy. I liked this one's use of varying sized boxes to represent the information, and some information being reachable from multiple flows, as this feels more realistic to a UI's navigations. From <a href="https://stock.adobe.com/search?k=hierarchy&amp;search_type=usertyped&amp;asset_id=404762100" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Adobe Stock</a></p>]]></content>
        <category label="WordJournal" term="WordJournal"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Finding Inspiration]]></title>
        <id>https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/finding-inspiration</id>
        <link href="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/finding-inspiration"/>
        <updated>2024-10-04T18:58:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Sketching a UI Inspired by Artwork]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="sketching-a-ui-inspired-by-artwork">Sketching a UI Inspired by Artwork<a class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Sketching a UI Inspired by Artwork" title="Direct link to Sketching a UI Inspired by Artwork" href="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/finding-inspiration#sketching-a-ui-inspired-by-artwork">​</a></h2>
<p>For this exercise, I visited my local art gallery, the Sheldon Museum of Art, to look over their collections in hopes of finding some inspiration for a UI design sketch. This piece, <em>Piazza Sigmund Freud (Milan, Italy)</em> by Lewis Baltz caught my eye. It is composed of three chromogenic prints that together show the parking lot of a railway station Lewis used during his time in Europe. Lewis saw an intensity in the unadulterated urban environment, unmistakably captured in the dramatic lighting of these photos.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="A snapshot of Piazza Sigmund Freud (Milan, Italy) taken in the gallery." src="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/assets/images/sheldonImage-6b7389ac72b7a2f810d81fe7211f0edb.jpg" width="4032" height="3024" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Lewis, B. (1989). <em>Piazza Sigmund Freud (Milan, Italy)</em>. [chromogenic color prints]. Sheldon Museum of Art. Lincoln, Nebraska, United States.
Photo taken by me.</p>
<p>Info about the piece's history was provided by The Sheldon. See the piece's page <a href="https://emp-web-95.zetcom.ch/eMP/eMuseumPlus?service=ExternalInterface&amp;module=collection&amp;objectId=45100&amp;viewType=detailView" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">here</a>.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="what-struck-me-about-the-piece">What Struck Me About the Piece<a class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What Struck Me About the Piece" title="Direct link to What Struck Me About the Piece" href="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/finding-inspiration#what-struck-me-about-the-piece">​</a></h2>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="emotive-colors">Emotive Colors<a class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Emotive Colors" title="Direct link to Emotive Colors" href="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/finding-inspiration#emotive-colors">​</a></h3>
<p>The most immediately striking part of this piece was its colors. The photos are primarily red and black, with more maroon tones within the gradients between the two. Red-lit environments have been found to increase tension, depression, and anxiety compared to white-lit environments, and the shadowy nature of the vast darkness surrounding the area only intensifies these feelings. I found it fascinating that such a limited color palette could evoke such a vivid atmosphere.</p>
<p>Source: <a href="https://www.frontiersin.org/journals/psychology/articles/10.3389/fpsyg.2022.938636/full" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://www.frontiersin.org/journals/psychology/articles/10.3389/fpsyg.2022.938636/full</a></p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="negative-space">Negative Space<a class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Negative Space" title="Direct link to Negative Space" href="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/finding-inspiration#negative-space">​</a></h3>
<p>I was drawn to this piece in part by its interesting use of negative space. An entire third of the triptych is negative space, with only a faint red-to-black gradient of the sky occupying the frame. This provides a sense of vastness: the cityscape itself seems large and sprawling, but the world around it is ever larger in a way that even the skyscrapers cannot match. The emptiness of the sky also contrasts visually with the business of the urban elements. Artist Adrian Reynolds explains that negative space has an emotional component of isolation and emptiness, which seems apt for this composition.</p>
<p>Source: <a href="https://adrianreynolds.ie/negative-space-in-art/#:~:text=In%20painting%2C%20negative%20space%20can,sense%20of%20movement%20or%20tension" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://adrianreynolds.ie/negative-space-in-art/#:~:text=In%20painting%2C%20negative%20space%20can,sense%20of%20movement%20or%20tension</a>.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="sectioning">Sectioning<a class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Sectioning" title="Direct link to Sectioning" href="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/finding-inspiration#sectioning">​</a></h3>
<p>This piece is a triptych, one piece separated into three component pieces. The individual pieces are quite different in their contents--one is just the sky, one is just the parking lot, and one has a hilly area leading up to more parking. This is the intrigue of triptychs as an art form; though there is a throughline among the pieces, each individual section is also an independent piece, allowed its own unique identity. Grouping of components is an important consideration in UI design as well, and though a traditional triptych wasn't what I envisioned for the UI, it got me thinking about the separation of different elements.</p>
<p>Source: <a href="https://www.riseart.com/guide/2414/what-is-a-triptych#:~:text=Triptych%20art%20is%20made%20up,new%20dimension%20to%20visual%20art" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://www.riseart.com/guide/2414/what-is-a-triptych#:~:text=Triptych%20art%20is%20made%20up,new%20dimension%20to%20visual%20art</a>.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="my-ui">My UI<a class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to My UI" title="Direct link to My UI" href="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/finding-inspiration#my-ui">​</a></h2>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="The UI created." src="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/assets/images/findingInspirationUI-0f54f2c09658c5c1a6cf5606ec4651df.png" width="1342" height="1196" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>In this UI, I hoped to replicate the intensity of the colors and the clever use of negative space. I used the photos’ color palette as a jumping off point, with black becoming my color for most components, red as the "negative space", and white for text.</p>
<p>I brightened up the colors to make the UI a bit more friendly than the intense and even dangerous atmosphere of the photos by playing up the transitional maroon and having my reds lean a bit more pink so they’d be perceived as gentler.</p>
<p>As for the negative space, I hoped to convey a sense of openness in this UI as the original photos achieved. I still tried to evoke a skyline with the gradient used as the background. I imagine in a full implementation there could be a subtle parallax effect as the user scrolls the page to the lower sections to enforce this idea of vastness.</p>
<p>The gradient also continues off to the side where I made the choice to have the section names not in the black portion, but atop the gradient, to match the contents they are shortcuts for. This was my attempt at playing with the grouping of elements, but instead of the original piece's strict separation of its sections, I wanted to experiment with mine bleeding into each other. By being a part of the gradient, the sections still feel a part of the content they interact with.</p>
<p>I imagine this would be a UI for a company who wants a sleek but exciting look, perhaps something like an activewear brand. The white font on black text feels very modern, but the pinkish-red gradient has an energy that contrasts the restrained, minimal look of the simple black and white. This UI is intended for web devices, due to its reliance on horizontal width.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="conclusion">Conclusion<a class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Conclusion" title="Direct link to Conclusion" href="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/finding-inspiration#conclusion">​</a></h2>
<p>This exercise was a useful lesson in how getting out of your comfort zone introduces you to new design ideas. Admittedly, this piece wasn’t the first one that caught my eye--I initially looked towards others that more closely suited my usual favorites in terms of colors especially. But, there was something boring and uninspired about the sketches produced from those. Looking for something new and striking pushed me in a constructive direction, and I’m pleased with the result.</p>]]></content>
        <category label="Studies" term="Studies"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Design Systems]]></title>
        <id>https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/design-systems</id>
        <link href="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/design-systems"/>
        <updated>2024-10-04T16:58:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Readings from Figma]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="readings-from-figma">Readings from Figma<a class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Readings from Figma" title="Direct link to Readings from Figma" href="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/design-systems#readings-from-figma">​</a></h2>
<p><em>Restraint is to design systems as menus are to restaurants.</em></p>
<p>The overarching theme of these articles is the importance of restraint in design systems. Keeping things simple may lead to sacrificing levels of detail that may seem undesirable at the time, but will make for easier management of the system moving forward. The more prescriptive the options are, the easier the rules are to follow, and the easier it is to make updates.</p>
<p>For example, the articles highlight the importance of limiting components within a system to maximize their reusability and ensure that there aren’t any components within the system that don’t have clear purpose, or overlap too significantly with another component’s functionality. Typefaces should also be chosen with careful consideration, limiting the number of variations in font, sizing, and other embellishments (such as bold or italic type) to create a more manageable set of options. Spacing should also have limited choices, such as a set increment system (such as in multiples of 8), both for visual consistency and for creating a clear rule.</p>
<p>This is not unlike the function of menus in restaurants—limited options, all which follow defined recipes to be made and served to customers. Without a menu, much like a design system without these rules, there would be chaos as there would be limitless options, and no guidelines on how to fulfill each order.</p>
<p>Source: <a href="https://www.designsystems.com/how-a-small-team-built-figma-dot-coms-design-system/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Figma Article on Design Layouts</a>, <a href="https://www.designsystems.com/space-grids-and-layouts/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Figma Article on Grids and Layouts</a>, <a href="https://www.designsystems.com/typography-guides/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Figma Article on Typography Guides</a>, <a href="https://www.designsystems.com/guide-to-content-strategy-in-design-systems/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Figma Article on Content Strategy</a></p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="A waiter attentively serves a pair of customers who are ordering off a menu." src="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/assets/images/designSystems-dcf9d286886f8f6794c9748a79df5e8a.jpeg" width="3000" height="2000" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>A waiter taking some customers' orders off a menu, much the way that a design system can provide options for a designer. From <a href="https://stock.adobe.com/search?k=waiter+restaurant&amp;search_type=usertyped&amp;asset_id=105370895" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Adobe Stock</a></p>]]></content>
        <category label="ApproximateAnalogy" term="ApproximateAnalogy"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Physiology Gallery Walk]]></title>
        <id>https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/physiology-gallery-walk</id>
        <link href="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/physiology-gallery-walk"/>
        <updated>2024-09-30T16:58:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[This page documents an activity where I, along with my design peers, did research on a concept of design physiology and/or psychology. My concept came from 100 Things Every Designer Needs to Know About People (Second Edition) by Susan Weinschenk, and centered on the perception of capitalized text.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This page documents an activity where I, along with my design peers, did research on a concept of design physiology and/or psychology. My concept came from <a href="https://www.oreilly.com/library/view/100-things-every/9780136746959/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">100 Things Every Designer Needs to Know About People (Second Edition)</a> by Susan Weinschenk, and centered on the perception of capitalized text.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="A photo of a poster with three major sections. The first is on major takeaways on the perception of capitalized text, particularly perceived urgency. The second is on this history of capitalized text, which showcases its use and headlines and its early associations with shouting. The third is a real world example of capitalized text on road signs, and some edited signs to display the same words in regular casing to illustrate the difference in tone." src="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/assets/images/physiologyExhibit-a26d3fba0a65e18149ab94459d186758.jpeg" width="4032" height="3024" class="img_ev3q"></p>]]></content>
        <category label="Studies" term="Studies"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Color Study]]></title>
        <id>https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/color-study</id>
        <link href="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/color-study"/>
        <updated>2024-09-26T16:58:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Analysis and Redesign of the Google Drive UI]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="analysis-and-redesign-of-the-google-drive-ui">Analysis and Redesign of the Google Drive UI<a class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Analysis and Redesign of the Google Drive UI" title="Direct link to Analysis and Redesign of the Google Drive UI" href="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/color-study#analysis-and-redesign-of-the-google-drive-ui">​</a></h2>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="A screenshot of the Google Drive UI" src="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/assets/images/colorStudyScreenshot-b40d4c92fc21e3cbb621b982957a8c15.png" width="512" height="242" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>This is the Google Drive UI, as seen by a browser user. It uses a primarily monochromatic palette of tones of blue, with the inclusion of white and (almost) black tones. Even the tones that appear gray are slightly blue-based. It also seems intentionally minimalistic, with its limited colors and significant use of white.</p>
<p>Blue, as discussed in <em>The Complete Color Harmony</em><sup><a id="user-content-fnref-1-f4c6aa" data-footnote-ref="true" aria-describedby="footnote-label" href="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/color-study#user-content-fn-1-f4c6aa">1</a></sup> is the most common color for UI design. For a utility app such as Drive, it seems to be a good choice. Calm is emphasized over excitement; nothing about using Drive demands much enthusiasm. It seems to strive for simplicity in both color and navigation. Blue is also a color associated with trustworthiness, a worthy concern for a product users trust to manage their files. I would expect the designers had exactly these goals in mind for what the UI would convey: calm, simplicity, and trust.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="replicating-the-ui">Replicating the UI<a class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Replicating the UI" title="Direct link to Replicating the UI" href="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/color-study#replicating-the-ui">​</a></h3>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="A rough replica of the Google Drive UI, where many icons have been simplified or removed." src="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/assets/images/colorStudyReplica-56d73cacb47eb0d9c6ee7ac31d03e4c9.png" width="800" height="400" class="img_ev3q">
This replica of the UI will be used to experiment with alternate color palettes. Generally, icons were simplified to open circles. The icons on the right hand side of the page were omitted as multiple of them are logos for other products. The multicolored Drive logo will remain an exception to the color palette, as with the original.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="alternate-palette-i-monochrome-orange">Alternate Palette I: Monochrome Orange<a class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Alternate Palette I: Monochrome Orange" title="Direct link to Alternate Palette I: Monochrome Orange" href="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/color-study#alternate-palette-i-monochrome-orange">​</a></h3>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="A recolor of the Google Drive UI that uses monochrome orange tones." src="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/assets/images/colorStudyPaletteI-440ba650c65b4c8ca502d02c0711bd09.png" width="800" height="400" class="img_ev3q">
For the first alternate palette, I wanted to experiment with value-driven colors. I kept the monochrome look of the original, but adjusted it to a color aligned with the functions of Drive. Drive enables communication, work, sociability, and creation, all traits associated with orange.</p>
<p>Orange is a departure from the original blue; to blue’s cool calmness, orange is close to the opposite, and can easily be seen as too much. Thus it was important to keep the brightness of this palette somewhat restrained in order to maintain the ease of viewing. Like the original, I freely allowed the use of white and black-adjacent tones to ensure this. The palette conveys more energy than the original, without becoming overwhelming.</p>
<p>This version of the palette was also a lesson in how colors appear differently on various screens. When viewing this on my phone screen, all the colors are undeniably orange. When viewed on my computer, the lighter tones appear almost pink. The romantic connotation of pink adds a much different feeling to the app than its intended orange shades do.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="alternate-palette-ii-complementary-chaos-triadic">Alternate Palette II: Complementary Chaos (Triadic)<a class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Alternate Palette II: Complementary Chaos (Triadic)" title="Direct link to Alternate Palette II: Complementary Chaos (Triadic)" href="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/color-study#alternate-palette-ii-complementary-chaos-triadic">​</a></h3>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="A recolor of the Google Drive UI, using the primary colors (red, yellow, blue), white, and black." src="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/assets/images/colorStudyPaletteII-3d6864540ecaa8bce9168e25f2d180f6.png" width="800" height="400" class="img_ev3q">
This palette was more of an exercise in what <em>not</em> to do. Most of Google’s products have the primary colors (plus green) on their logo, including Drive. This palette is not carried into the products themselves, most of which also use monochrome, minimalist color palettes. To observe why Google did not fully embrace this design convention, I created a triadic palette using the three primary colors: red, yellow, and blue.</p>
<p>Red and blue serve as calls to action, indicating something that can be interacted with or demands attention. Red indicates the simplest interactions, banners or highlights that only require a single click. Given red’s psychological spurring to fast action, this felt appropriate. This also placed the reds near the less contrasting yellow instead of blue in most instances. Blue is reserved for more thoughtful actions, such as searching for an item, opening and selecting from one of the dropdowns, or opening one of the suggested folders. The yellow is unimposing compared to its counterparts, so it was a serviceable background color.</p>
<p>It’s plain to see why Google kept their UIs less colorful. All the primaries together look busy and there is little meaning to be found within their clashing appearances and associations. The palette suggests something fun and unserious, quite the opposite of what the original conveys. Especially with the white included, it’s a palette that evokes clowns instead of a professional, simplistic utility app.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="alternate-palette-iii-icy-analogous">Alternate Palette III: Icy Analogous<a class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Alternate Palette III: Icy Analogous" title="Direct link to Alternate Palette III: Icy Analogous" href="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/color-study#alternate-palette-iii-icy-analogous">​</a></h3>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="A recolor of the Google Drive UI, using blue, blue-purple, and purple tones." src="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/assets/images/colorStudyPaletteIII-79a32da831d009609c258aafbfb875ab.png" width="800" height="400" class="img_ev3q">
For the final recolor, I wanted to try an analogous color palette. I find the original blue fitting, but took notice that some of its blues leaned closer to green while others had purple undertones. Thus, I fully committed to one direction by incorporating blue-purple and purple alongside the blue in its palette. I also wanted to try a palette that doesn’t use pure white as its “blank” color.</p>
<p>I opted for purples due to their creative and perspective-seeking personality associations, which seemed in alignment with the functionality of Drive. This design should still convey simplicity and color harmony like the original, but should ideally have more visual interest and perhaps a more contemplative connotation. The brighter shades of purple used evoke the whimsy of lavender more than the refinement associated with darker purples. Like the original, the cool tones make it easy on the eye and not especially energetic, but the added purple does pop out. The prominence of the light blues, much more omnipresent than on the original, give a bit of an icy look to the interface.</p>
<p>Despite having roughly the same amount of colors as the original, thanks to the loss of white, it no longer looks minimalistic and instead has a playful quality to it without being distracting. Still, this design doesn’t cast as wide a net as the original, lacking the mass appeal that a minimalist monochrome palette has.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="conclusions">Conclusions<a class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Conclusions" title="Direct link to Conclusions" href="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/color-study#conclusions">​</a></h3>
<p>An effective color palette should be both visually appealing and aligned with the app itself. So, which color scheme is ultimately the most effective? I believe the original best matches this definition, and this comes as no shock. A company with Google’s reputation likely went through an extensive experimentation process of their own before landing on this design, and it’s easy to see why it’s appealing. The simplicity of it reflects the simplicity of the app, the calming blue is usually a safe choice, and the minimalistic color usage doesn't risk upsetting anyone's personal tastes.</p>
<p>Of my own takes, I would say my monochrome orange is the best substitute. I enjoy the energy it provides the app, and I think the connotations of the color are reflective of the values this app helps people live out. There is something to be said about the diversified palettes, but at the end of the day each palette has a time and place, and in an app of Drive’s nature, less is usually more.</p>
<!-- -->
<section data-footnotes="true" class="footnotes"><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7 sr-only" id="footnote-label">Footnotes<a class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Footnotes" title="Direct link to Footnotes" href="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/color-study#footnote-label">​</a></h2>
<ol>
<li id="user-content-fn-1-f4c6aa">
<p>Interpretations of color connotations are informed by study of <em>The Complete Color Harmony, Pantone Edition: Expert Color Information for Professional Results</em> ---
Eiseman, L. (2017). <em>The complete color harmony, Pantone edition: Expert color information for professional color results</em>. Rockport Publishers. <a data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 1" class="data-footnote-backref" href="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/color-study#user-content-fnref-1-f4c6aa">↩</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>]]></content>
        <category label="Studies" term="Studies"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Colors II]]></title>
        <id>https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/colors-ii</id>
        <link href="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/colors-ii"/>
        <updated>2024-09-20T17:58:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Reading from The Complete Color Harmony, Pantone Edition: Expert Color Information for Professional Results]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="reading-from-the-complete-color-harmony-pantone-edition-expert-color-information-for-professional-results">Reading from <em>The Complete Color Harmony, Pantone Edition: Expert Color Information for Professional Results</em><a class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to reading-from-the-complete-color-harmony-pantone-edition-expert-color-information-for-professional-results" title="Direct link to reading-from-the-complete-color-harmony-pantone-edition-expert-color-information-for-professional-results" href="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/colors-ii#reading-from-the-complete-color-harmony-pantone-edition-expert-color-information-for-professional-results">​</a></h2>
<p>This section of reading covers both the conveyances of colors, and discusses the psychological ideas of what someone’s preferences in colors mean for their personality. Given the bulk of information, I decided to make myself a visual reference guide to lay out the information in a summarized manner. I chose to design this like a poster, or the concept art for what could be developed into one. I broke the drawing up into color zones where, in words, I wrote the associations of the respective color. For the personal color related information, I summarized the suggestions into a quick character drawing to accompany each section of the diagram, where the expression and pose of the character aim to convey what the reading suggests are characteristics of fans of the color. Beige is omitted from this poster due to the psychological overlap with brown, and the conveyance overlap with gray (and other neutrals). I wanted to have this so that I could see all the features of the colors side by side when considering color choices in my own works.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="A rough design for a poster showing major color categories (red, pink, orange, yellow, green, blue, lavender, purple, white, gray, black, and brown) along with words or feelings commonly associated with the colors. Each color also has a character posing in a way that reflects the personality traits associated with their color." src="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/assets/images/colorsIIart-1afbbc54305fa668340327416b434de4.png" width="1600" height="1600" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Source: Eiseman, L. (2017). <em>The complete color harmony, Pantone edition: Expert color information for professional color results</em>. Rockport Publishers.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="A set of crayons in the basic hues are arranged over a white background." src="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/assets/images/colorsII-e77eb335c90f06c3213a76cf8d5859a2.jpeg" width="2800" height="1803" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>I thought some crayons would be apt to match the idea of playing with colors--my earliest memories of art and learning the colors use this tool, and I'm finding a lot of the fun I had then in more thoughtful consideration of what my color choices convey. From <a href="https://stock.adobe.com/search?filters%5Bcontent_type%3Aphoto%5D=1&amp;filters%5Bcontent_type%3Aillustration%5D=1&amp;filters%5Bcontent_type%3Azip_vector%5D=1&amp;filters%5Bcontent_type%3Avideo%5D=1&amp;filters%5Bcontent_type%3Atemplate%5D=1&amp;filters%5Bcontent_type%3A3d%5D=1&amp;filters%5Bfetch_excluded_assets%5D=1&amp;filters%5Binclude_stock_enterprise%5D=1&amp;filters%5Bcontent_type%3Aimage%5D=1&amp;k=crayons&amp;order=relevance&amp;safe_search=1&amp;search_page=1&amp;search_type=autosuggest&amp;acp=0&amp;aco=cray&amp;get_facets=0&amp;asset_id=7309905" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Adobe Stock</a></p>]]></content>
        <category label="FreeForm" term="FreeForm"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Colors I]]></title>
        <id>https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/colors-i</id>
        <link href="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/colors-i"/>
        <updated>2024-09-20T16:58:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Reading from The Complete Color Harmony, Pantone Edition: Expert Color Information for Professional Results]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="reading-from-the-complete-color-harmony-pantone-edition-expert-color-information-for-professional-results">Reading from <em>The Complete Color Harmony, Pantone Edition: Expert Color Information for Professional Results</em><a class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to reading-from-the-complete-color-harmony-pantone-edition-expert-color-information-for-professional-results" title="Direct link to reading-from-the-complete-color-harmony-pantone-edition-expert-color-information-for-professional-results" href="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/colors-i#reading-from-the-complete-color-harmony-pantone-edition-expert-color-information-for-professional-results">​</a></h2>
<p>This section introduced some fundamental principles of color, including vocabulary such as hue, saturation, value, tone, and undertone. It also discussed the interplay between colors within palettes. The color wheel serves as an easy visual reference for the relationships between the colors, from which we can obtain several conventions for color combinations.</p>
<p>A monotone palette consists of a neutral color (off-white, gray, beige, etc.) in varying tones.</p>
<p>A monochrome palette is varying shades of a non-neutral hue (red, yellow, blue, etc.).</p>
<p>An analogous palette uses three adjacent families on the color wheel, most popularly a primary (red, yellow, blue), secondary (orange, green, purple), and a tertiary (red purple, orange red, yellow orange, yellow green, blue green, and blue purple) that all sit adjacent on the wheel.</p>
<p>Complementary color schemes make use of colors opposite each other on the wheel, and may include a neutral buffer. This can further be split into split complementary (a hue and the two on either side of its complement), triads (three equidistant hues on the wheel), or tetrads (two sets of complements for four total colors).</p>
<p>I found the discussion on palette selection especially interesting, so I wanted to test them out for myself by making different palettes for the same simple UI that satisfied each of the major categories (monotone, monochrome, analogous, and complementary).</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="A set of four clones of the same simple UI that have been given varying color palettes: one with varying tones of beige; one with varying tones of green; one with blue, green, and blue-green; and one that is beige, orange, and blue." src="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/assets/images/colorsIsketches-e42fdc770076ae9a4fe0dd721d37955c.png" width="512" height="512" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>For simplicity, this UI is just a generic header and footer, designed to have 3 colors in their shared palette (plus white for the negative space).</p>
<p>The monotone attempt is just varying shades of beige. Like the text predicts, it’s inoffensive, but not eye catching and does little to hold my interest, especially next to its more colorful counterparts.</p>
<p>The monochrome version is elevated by its pop of color, but the lack of contrast still leaves something to be desired. I find my eye drawn toward others before it.</p>
<p>Analogous is my personal favorite of the bunch. Next to the blue-green intermediary, both the blue and green used here take on a bit of the other color, leading to a more seamless look. This one also required the most experimentation, where I found that the blue or green didn’t look right as the dropdown color because the contrast became much more apparent when they were side by side.</p>
<p>For complementary, I used an orange and blue combination, along with a neutral buffer color like the text suggests. This makes the design more tame and prevents the visual vibration where the colors would otherwise overlap. Next to orange, the beige appears warmer than it does in the monotone version (it’s the exact same color!), so the blue of the text doesn’t lose its contrasting effect despite the buffer. Still, the warm orange seems to draw attention more quickly than the blue used for the text.</p>
<p>Source: Eiseman, L. (2017). <em>The complete color harmony, Pantone edition: Expert color information for professional color results</em>. Rockport Publishers.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="A graphic showing the color wheel." src="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/assets/images/colorsI-6580705a9f4e3206325f1345fdea77d3.jpeg" width="3693" height="3693" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>A color wheel that even breaks up its hues into their varying tones, to showcase the vast possibilities that exist in color and palette construction. From <a href="https://stock.adobe.com/search?filters%5Bcontent_type%3Aphoto%5D=1&amp;filters%5Bcontent_type%3Aillustration%5D=1&amp;filters%5Bcontent_type%3Azip_vector%5D=1&amp;filters%5Bcontent_type%3Avideo%5D=1&amp;filters%5Bcontent_type%3Atemplate%5D=1&amp;filters%5Bcontent_type%3A3d%5D=1&amp;filters%5Bfetch_excluded_assets%5D=1&amp;filters%5Binclude_stock_enterprise%5D=1&amp;filters%5Bcontent_type%3Aimage%5D=1&amp;k=color+wheel&amp;order=relevance&amp;safe_search=1&amp;limit=100&amp;search_page=1&amp;search_type=usertyped&amp;acp=&amp;aco=color+wheel&amp;get_facets=0&amp;asset_id=327278459" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Adobe Stock</a></p>]]></content>
        <category label="SketchInspo" term="SketchInspo"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Aesthetic Design]]></title>
        <id>https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/aesthetic-design</id>
        <link href="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/aesthetic-design"/>
        <updated>2024-09-17T16:58:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Reading from Garr Reynolds's Presentation Zen: Simple Ideas on Presentation Design and Delivery Chapter 6]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="reading-from-garr-reynoldss-presentation-zen-simple-ideas-on-presentation-design-and-delivery-chapter-6">Reading from Garr Reynolds's <em>Presentation Zen: Simple Ideas on Presentation Design and Delivery</em> Chapter 6<a class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to reading-from-garr-reynoldss-presentation-zen-simple-ideas-on-presentation-design-and-delivery-chapter-6" title="Direct link to reading-from-garr-reynoldss-presentation-zen-simple-ideas-on-presentation-design-and-delivery-chapter-6" href="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/aesthetic-design#reading-from-garr-reynoldss-presentation-zen-simple-ideas-on-presentation-design-and-delivery-chapter-6">​</a></h2>
<p><strong>Balance</strong>. This word describes the principles found in the section of the text that describes the three outlying design principles (i.e. not the big four). In practice, this means careful consideration of the interplay between design elements and how a designer should strive to achieve something that conveys the appropriate amount of information, in a sensible way, with the appropriate amount of embellishment. For example, the signal-to-noise ratio relates to the amount of signals on a design (i.e. information with some crucial purpose) versus noise (anything on the design which is not conveying information). Reynolds suggests trying to achieve the highest ratio possible, such that the signals far outweigh the noise in a contained design. Balance can also be considered in less obvious aspects of design, such as in the use of images. As described in the picture superiority effect, people more readily remember words than images–we should strive not to overwhelm users with descriptive text that could have its effect achieved much more simply by an image. At the same time, text is not without place, and can be used to label or relate images. Spacing is also another aspect of design where balance is key. Empty space has a place in design, both to avoid overcrowding of information, and to enable grouping of related elements through differential spacing.</p>
<p>Source: Reynolds, G. (2019). <em>Presentation zen: Simple ideas on presentation design and delivery</em> (Third edition). New Riders.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="A scale constructed of stones. A large stone sits in balance with the four smaller stones stacked on the other side." src="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/assets/images/aestheticDesign-ccc2ec75f9e71603b5b06c0a4663412c.jpeg" width="3600" height="2395" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>I chose this image to represent the signal-to-noise ratio. The stacked stones may represent units of signal, while the singular stone represents noise. A lot of signal is best to balance out any noise. From <a href="https://stock.adobe.com/search?load_type=search&amp;is_recent_search=&amp;search_type=autosuggest&amp;k=scales&amp;native_visual_search=&amp;similar_content_id=&amp;acp=0&amp;aco=scales&amp;asset_id=70247872" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Adobe Stock</a></p>]]></content>
        <category label="WordJournal" term="WordJournal"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Design Rules]]></title>
        <id>https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/design-rules</id>
        <link href="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/design-rules"/>
        <updated>2024-09-12T16:58:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Reading from Steven Krug's Don't Make Me Think, Revisited: A Common Sense Approach to Web Usability Chapters 2-5]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="reading-from-steven-krugs-dont-make-me-think-revisited-a-common-sense-approach-to-web-usability-chapters-2-5">Reading from Steven Krug's <em>Don't Make Me Think, Revisited: A Common Sense Approach to Web Usability</em> Chapters 2-5<a class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to reading-from-steven-krugs-dont-make-me-think-revisited-a-common-sense-approach-to-web-usability-chapters-2-5" title="Direct link to reading-from-steven-krugs-dont-make-me-think-revisited-a-common-sense-approach-to-web-usability-chapters-2-5" href="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/design-rules#reading-from-steven-krugs-dont-make-me-think-revisited-a-common-sense-approach-to-web-usability-chapters-2-5">​</a></h2>
<p><strong>Information without intentionality is like a library without an organization system.</strong> If there is no organization scheme to the books in a library, it would be nearly impossible for someone to find what they were searching for. They would be overwhelmed by the sheer amount of information with little distinction between each item. Even the books’ diversity in sizes, colors, and fonts would become overstimulating and difficult to parse through with such a large collection. Most people wouldn’t know where to start–or have the patience to even try.</p>
<p>The messaging in these chapters of Krug’s writing is that the same idea goes for UI design, where information should have clear intent and organization behind it. Walls of text, despite their higher word counts, ultimately give less information to a user who typically won’t devote the time or effort to anything more than skimming a site. A design tailored to emphasize the information that matters and eliminate that which has no purpose will serve much like an organization system in a library, allowing users to understand what information is where and, among that information, what is of interest to them.</p>
<p>Visual hierarchies, elimination of unnecessary words, and sparing use of visual indicators like animations or bold, large fonts are just a few of the ways to achieve this effect. Library organizational systems, much like design conventions, are usually well-established and should only be overturned in favor of something that clearly works better. To change something in a way that goes against the expectations of a user without improving their experience only adds more confusion.</p>
<p>Source: Krug, S. (2014). <em>Don’t make me think, revisited: A common sense approach to web usability</em> (Third edition). New Riders. <a href="https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.5555/2663393" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Link</a></p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="A magnifying glass is help up to a page filled with blurry text. Even the words being magnified are distorted, with no real meaning being discerned from the mentions of &amp;quot;cosmic rays&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;science&amp;quot;, and &amp;quot;technology&amp;quot;." src="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/assets/images/dmmt1image-e01e85577cc979974763c3db2670fd0b.png" width="1200" height="798" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Much like a UI design, if I don’t have a sense of how these books are organized, I won’t be able to find the information I came for. None of the books so much as stand out to give me any sense of where to look. <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/stewart/99129170/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Original Image (no modifications were made)</a>.</p>]]></content>
        <category label="ApproximateAnalogy" term="ApproximateAnalogy"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Shneiderman & Info Organization]]></title>
        <id>https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/shneiderman-info-org</id>
        <link href="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/shneiderman-info-org"/>
        <updated>2024-09-06T16:58:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Reading from Ben Shneiderman's “The Eyes Have It: A Task by Data Type Taxonomy for Information Visualizations”]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="reading-from-ben-shneidermans-the-eyes-have-it-a-task-by-data-type-taxonomy-for-information-visualizations">Reading from Ben Shneiderman's “The Eyes Have It: A Task by Data Type Taxonomy for Information Visualizations”<a class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Reading from Ben Shneiderman's “The Eyes Have It: A Task by Data Type Taxonomy for Information Visualizations”" title="Direct link to Reading from Ben Shneiderman's “The Eyes Have It: A Task by Data Type Taxonomy for Information Visualizations”" href="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/shneiderman-info-org#reading-from-ben-shneidermans-the-eyes-have-it-a-task-by-data-type-taxonomy-for-information-visualizations">​</a></h2>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="A screenshot from the UNL campus map, which shows the user having clicked on the Nebraska Union building." src="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/assets/images/schneidermanuiexample-937c69152fef323635a2341f577f3364.png" width="1600" height="536" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>This section of reading focused on data visualization and organization, particularly emphasizing the idea that a good UI should begin with an overview, enable zooming and filtering, and provide details to users on demand. This ensures that the information a user is given is tailored to what they came for, without the distractions of irrelevant information. Tools like keeping an action history can also aid users in navigating a UI, especially if they want to save the filters they applied, or go back to choose new details to demand. I chose to examine the <a href="https://maps.unl.edu/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">UNL campus map website</a> as an example of this UI philosophy, which I consider to be a functional if not especially appealing UI design. By default, this displays a very zoomed out version of the map where all the campuses are visible, with the shapes of relevant buildings displayed but no additional information on the significance of any individual building (overview). Clicking on one of the campuses, using the zoom tools on the side of the map, or searching for a building by name or abbreviation will narrow the field of view (zoom/filter). Only by confirming your interest by clicking on or searching for an individual building, then clicking on the “Get Directions” prompt, will a user be redirected to a tailored route between their location and the desired building (details on demand). This is also a usage of Shneiderman’s basic example of a 2-dimensional data display for a geographic map. It doesn’t follow all of Shneiderman’s advice, though: the system of undoing actions is fairly broken, only really able to achieve combining the previous and current terms in the search bar.</p>
<p>Source: “The Eyes Have It: A Task by Data Type Taxonomy for Information Visualizations” by Ben Shneiderman (1996)</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="A magnifying glass is help up to a page filled with blurry text. Even the words being magnified are distorted, with no real meaning being discerned from the mentions of &amp;quot;cosmic rays&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;science&amp;quot;, and &amp;quot;technology&amp;quot;." src="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/assets/images/shneidermanimage-ad091397ccff154126e090e525cdbf06.png" width="1200" height="800" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>An image to represent the confusion and chaos that can arise from trying to navigate a UI where all the details are displayed without the user's demand. <a href="https://pxhere.com/en/photo/1259367#google_vignette" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Original Image</a></p>]]></content>
        <category label="DirectedAnalysis" term="DirectedAnalysis"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Affordances & Signifiers II]]></title>
        <id>https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/affordances-signifiers-ii</id>
        <link href="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/affordances-signifiers-ii"/>
        <updated>2024-08-30T16:01:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Reading from Don Norman's The Design of Everyday Things Chapter 2]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="reading-from-don-normans-the-design-of-everyday-things-chapter-2">Reading from Don Norman's <em>The Design of Everyday Things</em> Chapter 2<a class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to reading-from-don-normans-the-design-of-everyday-things-chapter-2" title="Direct link to reading-from-don-normans-the-design-of-everyday-things-chapter-2" href="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/blog/affordances-signifiers-ii#reading-from-don-normans-the-design-of-everyday-things-chapter-2">​</a></h2>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="A flow chart illustrating the stages of action as described by Don Norman." src="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/assets/images/AffordancesandSignifiersIIconceptmap-1ffd9112b8197c8c87101c2465e818b1.png" width="2550" height="3000" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>To start off my flow chart, I replicated the flow of stages of action as described in the textbook. Circles around the subsets of stages separate the gulf of execution and the gulf of evaluation. From there, I tried to tie in concepts from the previous chapter by applying the principles of design to these stages. The textbook is more detailed about the role of feedback in the evaluation stage, as it gives users information with which to make their evaluations. The text spent most of its time emphasizing signifiers as a means of feedforward, the information used to guide our execution. In addition to those signifiers, I noted down conceptual models and (logical) mappings as tools users might reflect on in this stage to plan their interaction with the item. I also denoted the outcomes that may occur once a goal has been attempted (i.e. the compare phase is over). If a user struggles to use an item or cannot figure out how to revise their behavior, they may experience learned helplessness and blame themself for the designer’s poor design choices. If given the right information, they will hopefully have a positive user experience with the item in question. This flowchart optimistically leaves off what happens if a user simply has a bad experience without blaming themself.</p>
<p>Source: Norman, D. (2013). <em>The design of everyday things.</em> Basic Books. <a href="https://jnd.org/books/the-design-of-everyday-things-revised-and-expanded-edition/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Link</a></p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="A man is sitting on the floor with his head hidden in his arms. An electronic watch is on his wrist." src="https://kbreit2.github.io/katelyn-portfolio-template/assets/images/AffordancesandSignifiersIIimage-07c6ff9e953b1eec57a1eee4395c51ae.jpg" width="1280" height="960" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>I was looking for an image to convey the sense of learned helplessness that can come from failure to grasp a design that lacks proper feedback. This image portrays someone wearing an electronic watch, which reminded me of the section in the text where the author muses about how watches are housing an increasing amount of functions and becoming less straightforward to use in the process. So, this image represents the learned helplessness you might experience if you cannot intuit how to navigate your e-watch. <a href="https://pixabay.com/photos/man-depressed-sitting-on-the-floor-2734073/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Original Image</a></p>]]></content>
        <category label="ConceptMap" term="ConceptMap"/>
    </entry>
</feed>